The slow passage of time on objects
exposes these [music] to all kinds of
aggression.
External agents [music] and human
activity act on them, damaging them,
wearing them out, rusting them, rotting
them.
Water, fire, [music] insects, and
microorganisms are together with man
their fiercest enemies.
What makes [music] man different from
the other forces is that they are the
only ones who can stop or hold back the
process which without their intervention
would be [music] irreversible.
Scientific [music] interest in art
conservation has developed over the last
century based on science and technology.
The main criterion [music] is that
nothing that is external or foreign to
the piece should be added. In those
cases where it is essential to
transgress [music] this general
principle, two requirements should be
rigorously met.
Whatever has been added should be
clearly appreciated
and it should also be possible to remove
it without this jeopardizing the
integrity of the hole.
Moreover, in many cases, it is necessary
for the piece of work to recover [music]
its function and arrangement.
These requirements are the result of the
experience accumulated by curators
[music]
who have learned that a piece of work is
never definitively restored.
Technical advances occur very quickly
and respect [music] for what could be
done in the future makes restoers work
cautiously so that their current
intervention doesn't obstruct [music]
future restorations.
The artworks and objects of cultural
interest that [music] fill the display
cases of museums only represent a tiny
fraction of human production over the
years.
They are not [music] even representative
of the total quantity of artworks that
have been preserved up until our time.
And that's because [music] the majority
of the world's artistic heritage is not
on display. It is stored in security
facilities treasured for its commercial
value which does not always coincide
with its value as an artwork.
[music]
Safes reinforced vaults and underground
stores protected against fire, flooding
and [music] earthquakes hide thousands
and thousands of pieces that were at
some moment made for collective use and
enjoyment. Thousands of treasures hidden
from the light of day, which nonetheless
need to be [music] preserved.
A scientific point of view has been so
important in the development of criteria
[music] for artistic restoration that
the need became clear to create
specialized centers provided with the
latest technologies to carry out this
huge task.
One of these centers [music] is the
Spanish Cultural Heritage Institute.
Its radial architecture clearly
expresses the convergence of the
different branches of art and science.
That is its aim. [music]
The work carried out here is done based
on the exchange of information among the
different disciplines. A permanent
dialogue between analysts and
technicians by which in [music] the end
culture and art are strengthened.
[singing]
The teams of experts that work here are
up to date with the most modern lines of
research into techniques and science
applied to the conservation of heritage.
In the laboratories, analysis work is
done that facilitates the work of
curators and restorers at the center.
Here, analysis is done on pigments,
varnishes, glues, mortars, paper, wood,
parchment, inks, metal, and other
materials that man has learned to use to
express his dreams.
The electron microscope, dedicated
exclusively to the field of art
conservation, is essential for
day-to-day work.
Diving into the microscopic universe,
the specialist curator can find out much
of great interest when it comes to
undertaking intervention. For example,
it is possible to [music] penetrate into
the interior of the supports used by
artists and to determine their nature
with a [music] high degree of accuracy.
Using a tiny splinter extracted from
[music] the back of a painted board, it
is possible to establish the kind of
wood that the artist used as a support.
The restoration process will proceed
[music] according to the outcome of this
test.
The cent's documentation records are
very important.
A highly specialized library on artistic
and technical matters allows information
to be obtained beforehand for each
project. A great many specialized books
and journals are kept here.
An extensive photographic library
includes [music] different archives
holding plates of great interest in
terms of artistic heritage since
photography began.
Analyzing these plates, which are
sometimes more than a century old, and
comparing them with a work's current
state, the curator can obtain crucial
information when it comes to
intervention.
Faced with the challenge of [music]
deteriorating artworks,
the curator can tackle conservation and
restoration treatment in different ways.
In some cases and with some works like
this art nuvo lamp from the beginning of
the century, the aesthetic and
decorative value is foremost. And so the
piece must be treated, cleaned, and
conserved to eliminate all the problems
that might be present.
In other cases, pieces may have a
religious or cultural value such as this
terraota which comes from aa and which
symbolizes a punic tanier. This piece
must be treated according to certain
scientific and technical criteria and
the aim is to prepare it for exhibition
and display.
The analytical possibilities that the
new exploration systems offer the
curator provide him or her with a solid
foundation on which to base his or her
criteria for intervening in the work
from the purely material point of view.
Once the greatest possible amount of
specific data about its material [music]
condition has been extracted from the
piece, it is then analyzed as a human
work. This means investigating the
historical and personal circumstances
[music] of its creation with the aim of
achieving an in-depth understanding of
the object's essence.
Then the conservator turns to technology
for the intervention, paying attention
to the general maxims of restoration,
but never forgetting that each piece is
different to others [music] and this
requires individual treatment.
X-rays show us what is hidden without
damaging the surface, which makes them
perfect for art restoration,
whose general criteria involve above all
preserving the original.
The institute's radiology department
contributes to the overall task with
powerful equipment
able to work at a very high degree of
penetration, which [clears throat] means
that the room must be very well
insulated.
Here work is done on pieces whose sizes
and nature vary considerably and the
information that is extracted
constitutes [music]
valuable material for those who will
later undertake the intervention.
The X-rays of large [music] wooden
sculptures, for example, reveal the
presence in the interior of metallic
elements which may or may not be
integral parts of the piece. [music]
On other occasions, what the X-rays
[music] show underneath the visible
paint layer are not corrections or
changes, but complete works which due to
the extreme poverty of the artists
[music] were reused as supports for new
paintings.
[music]
One of the most curious cases to have
happened in this radiology [music]
department was the discovery that this
work by Ritzy St. Ignatius [music] of
Antioch was made up of two hidden works
which radiation revealed to have been
sewn together and then used for the new
work.
[music]
spectral images that overlap art that
exists and which at the same time does
not.
X-rays are also used with extraordinary
results to [music] examine the contents
of very ancient documents written on
metallic supports that have become very
corroded. This is the [music] case with
this bronze plaque, the support for a
document that could be essential for
further knowledge of [music] the ancient
Tiberian language.
The responsibility of the restorer
[music] of this document with its great
informative value is lessened once the
X-ray of the piece has been carried out.
[music]
Even if the later cleaning techniques
create confusion or loss of signs in the
[music] text, this is nonetheless
preserved by the X-ray. Its words will
be preserved [music] for history.
There is an ever growing desire to
[music] make heritage conservation an
obligation to bequeath to posterity
those items that history has [music]
left to us.
That is why the restorer needs to access
all kinds of procedures whether they are
mechanical, [music] chemical or in the
case of this piece steam brushing or the
preparation of puses or gels able to
penetrate the most inaccessible cracks.
Aware of the appearance of new
techniques that can be applied to their
work, restorers carry out cleaning using
everything from lasers able to [music]
discriminate between colors to
ultrasonic devices adapted from those
used by dentists for dental cleaning.
The institute's documents and book
service [music] has developed its own
system for the cleaning and recovery of
very carbonated lead seals which
consists of occasional electrolysis
[music] using platinum electrodes and
acidulated water. And this is completed
with subsequent washing and the
application of a synthetic resin to
protect the metal surface.
So the seals remained linked to the
documents forming a protected hole that
allows them to be consulted by scholars.
This document has been seriously damaged
by the chemical substances that make up
the inks which can have very diverse
natures. Sometimes their acidic nature
can burn the paper acting as a support.
However, there are occasions on which
the acidity contributes [music] to
preserving the original writing instead
of destroying it. This is the case with
the information contained on the 17th
century labels that appeared on the back
of this set of panel paintings by
Fanfiscoco Thubaran. Although a large
part of the label has been lost, [music]
the ink burnt the paper and reached the
surface of the wood and the marks of the
writing were imprinted on it.
On the side entrance doors of the
sacquarium, he painted two angels in
life size with sensors in their hands.
And in the corridor leading to the tidy
parts of this aquarium, paintings of
some clerics of this order can be seen
in life-size which are admirably carried
out and very natural-looking with
realistic expressions and excellent
Jarroscuro. This is how an 18th century
traveler describes these paintings which
made up part of the ensemble in the
Casuzian monastery of Herth de la until
they were taken from where they hung and
transferred to the Kadith Museum.
There is a mystery behind these works.
They were designed as an ordered set and
nobody took the trouble at the time to
write down the arrangement.
Now, thanks to the labels that have
appeared on their backs, it has finally
been possible to determine the
arrangement and they can be correctly
displayed.
This fulfills another of the maxims of
restoration. [music] What has been
conceived as a whole should be restored
as such. The artistic importance of the
Thurbaran Ensembler has meant that
[music] restoration has been tackled in
a particularly detailed and systematic
manner. Contemporary critics
wholeheartedly agree with the opinion of
the traveler and they consider these
works to be highly representative of the
artist's expressive mature period.
Subaran was 40 when he completed them
and was at a crucial point in his
career.
Art restoration professionals are
obliged to seek the support of whatever
sciences may help to carry out their
[music] task in the best possible way.
They must make decisions with full
knowledge of [music] what they are doing
in order to avoid irreparable errors.
This is why they draw up an overall
[music] analysis plan whose results will
guide intervention.
In this case, a paint [music] sample was
taken to establish the chemical nature
of its components.
This is a delicate operation that
[music] always damages the work.
However, fortunately, the analytical
[music] capacity of a modern laboratory
that specializes in artworks, like the
[music] institute's chemistry
department, does not require large
samples.
The operations that are carried out with
each sample are no less delicate than
its extraction. What is sought is
[music] to identify the nature of the
different strata that make up the paint
layer.
and so it must be looked at side on. In
order to make it possible to handle, the
analyst puts it in a block of synthetic
resin that will then be reduced to the
point where the sample can be accessed.
From this moment on, handling must be
done extremely carefully since the
smallest [music] error will mean an
irreplaceable loss.
[music]
For those who know how to look, the
strategraphic cutting [music] of a layer
of paint contains precious information
about varnishes, pigments, primers, and
preparations.
Magnified enough times, these samples
reveal important data about the artist's
way [music] of working and preferences
and also about the successive versions
that the work experienced [music] over
time.
[music]
In this humble, the existence of a red
repainted layer can be seen over the
original strata. [music]
This is a valuable piece of information
that once known to the creator [music]
helps to make decisions.
Finally, a third sample shows evidence
of the existence of a thick layer of
oxidized [music] varnish that distorts
the original coloring of the work.
However, what we see under the
microscope is not enough when we want to
know the chemical nature of the strata
that make up the paint layer.
This is crucially important information
for those who are to intervene in the
work since incorrect treatment may cause
interactions between the different
chemical substances present and could
badly damage the piece.
A computerized analysis device is used
for this and its results establish the
nature of these samples components and
so the products and processes most
appropriate for its treatment are
defined in such a way that the restorers
can carry out their work safely.
They now know that the elimination of
the layers of oxidized varnish is
[music] possible and desirable and they
act on this information.
The aid of X-rays is essential for an
in-depth analysis of the works. With
their help, the institute's radiology
service has fully studied the subarans
from the Herth monastery.
By penetrating the successive layers of
the paintings, a new universe of
information about the creative process
is revealed. The phases of this process
are shown and parameters for comparison
are set covering what conclusions can be
reached both as regards the ensemble and
each work in particular.
It is too often forgotten that the
paintings are not always [music] works
by a single artist. Many great master
painters had workshops of helpers who
took responsibility for the most routine
and laborious tasks.
Later on, the master intervened in order
to complete or correct the work.
Many of these interventions can be
detected today with great accuracy
[music]
thanks to radiology.
The comparative analysis of these pieces
allows the specialists to debate over
the degree of intervention by the master
thouan in each of these.
Here comparison is based on something as
subtle as the type of brushstroke used
by the artist. Its uniformity, its
vigor, its fluidity.
It is also possible to ascertain the
order followed when carrying out the
painting. When we see the complete head
of a bishop under a miter, it is then
possible to say that the head was
painted whole to make the miter fit more
easily later on.
In [music] these details, a specialized
analyst finds much informative material
that sometimes completely refutes
current theories.
>> [music]
>> The artistic restorer also has available
an exploration procedure that is [music]
similar to X-rays.
Although with the added advantage that
safety measures are not needed to use it
[music]
refletography involves using infrared
[music] radiation to penetrate beyond
the visible surface of the painting,
revealing the consecutive [music] stages
of creating the painting from the first
sketch on the canvas.
The information taken by curators with
these explorations can be crucial for
their work.
Penetrating further and further into the
work, it [music] is possible to observe
the preparatory drawings of the artist,
often done with a charcoal.
These lines show the initial idea, the
one that the painter had about his work
before starting it.
These are embionic marks which would
later be followed to a greater or lesser
extent by the artist in the creative
[music] process that followed.
The treatments required by the
conservation of contemporary artworks
make up a separate chapter in the set of
artistic conservation techniques.
The institutions that specialize in this
kind of works like Madrid's Raina Sophia
Museum are obliged to respond
dynamically to the demands that arise
with the deterioration of very different
materials that are all too often
ephemeral.
It is clear then that the details of art
conservation cannot be built up into a
system. This is an occasional task which
only makes sense with respect to the
specific work it is applied to.
It is neither a science nor a craft but
the result of a chain of considerations.
The first of which is to [music] respect
the artistic object as the result of the
artist's intention.
The absolute liberalization of aesthetic
[music] criteria that occurred
throughout the last century means that
artists use all kinds of materials
[music] that were never before thought
of as artistic supports.
There is no [music] limit that has not
been transgressed. Back then, nobody
thought that time would [music] also act
on those inflammatory and daring works.
But time has passed.
In this painting, the painter Bengham
Baluthia introduced a number of elements
into the traditional oil like oak leaves
and feathers that have been lost from a
number of areas. Before treatment, the
aim was to reproduce these same
materials that the artist had used. This
was done with a series of samples that
were aged in a laboratory chamber and
then a number of adhesives were [music]
tested out to see which was best before
being applied.
The conservation workshops of the Reno
Sophia Museum have the necessary [music]
resources to meet different challenges.
The works [music] restored here are some
of the most important in contemporary
art.
Consequently, its work methods integrate
very advanced analytical systems and any
technique that may be adapted to its
restoration work, such as the settlement
of the paint layer by applying heat
using infrared rays.
As for the workshop, the most modern
techniques rub shoulders with other more
traditional ones in accordance with the
needs of each piece. Since once again,
general rules must submit to the
peculiarities of each piece of work.
[music]
What is common to all cases is the need
for information about their condition
and infrared reftography [music]
decisively contributes to this.
The working methods [music] followed in
the study of contemporary art are
basically similar to those followed in
the study of [music] works from previous
periods. However, it is necessary to
bear in mind the unique nature of the
work that is to be analyzed and
specifically the different materials
used.
It is surprising that artistic supports
have varied so little over time.
Although they used very different
chemical substances, both Picasso and
Jur used canvas backings and oil paint
to create their works. Likewise, both
Jurers and Picasso's works can be
analyzed using the strategraphic [music]
technique.
[music]
Unlike other centers with more of a
hierarchy, the [music] decisions in this
department are taken after each of the
creators expresses and defends his or
her opinion on the matter.
These are often decisions on very
specific [music] matters. For example,
this is the case with this mobile by
Anel Faran called Muher Aendosa with the
members of the team debating over the
suitability of replacing the hemp cord
that joins the pieces with another one
of similar characteristics or the
alternative of strengthening and
consolidating the [music] original
chord.
The crux of the matter lies in
establishing whether the chord as an
object forms an essential part of the
piece or whether on the other hand it is
only a necessary element because of its
function but its nature is irrelevant
for the whole work. [music]
This Miro sculpture of cast bronze with
welded iron bars was subjected to
[music] study for packaging since it was
requested for an exhibition to stop it
suffering damage as has happened [music]
here with this small deformation.
[music] Other times the problems are
very similar to those that occur with
older works. For example, this polished
sculpture by the magnificent [music]
sculptor Alberto. We encounter the
problem of recovering the original
patina which must have been [music] very
similar to the one shown on this other
similar sculpture.
[music]
Curators of contemporary art often have
the privilege to receive the best
possible advice for the restoration of
works that given by [music] the artists
themselves who in many cases are still
alive and working.
In cases where the painters are no
longer alive, the family is requested to
provide all the documentation possible,
including notes, videos, and photographs
[music] about the artist's way of
working or the brands of paint used.
Information that can be very valuable
when it comes to restoration.
[music]
The artists responses to the restoration
of their works is very different in each
case. There are those who resist the
idea of restoration and those who work
closely with the creator providing
information about the materials used and
the work system.
This information is filed and it will be
very useful for future interventions in
that artist's works.
Many of the works in the Raina Sophia
Museum's collection are drawings and
paintings on paper.
The process of restoring this graphite
and India ink drawing, a work by the
painter Ben Hamin Balenthia, has a
number of stages.
First mechanical cleaning is done to
remove surface dirt that has become
stuck. And then tests are done with
solvents of various kinds to eliminate
the yellowish stains of some substance
until one that works is found.
After studying the specific conditions
of the work, cleaning is carried out. If
necessary, following a laborious method
that consists of the occasional
application of minimal quantities of
solvent using glass capillary tubes, or
if not, the art object is worked on
under a special hood that lasts until
cleaning is complete.
Anthropology is a science whose limits
[music] are as vague as people's lives.
And anthropological museums are the
results of the human urge to [music]
collect and analyze the information that
humans ourselves produce. Here there are
objects that [music] were familiar to
our parents, to our grandparents, worn
utensils polished by contact with human
skin.
Instruments that let us escape from
cold, hunger, loneliness.
Tools that helped us make life more
comfortable. Companions on our species
long voyage through time. [music]
Survivals.
Without a rigorous order, an
anthropology museum's stores would come
to look like a [music] giant auction
house because of the great variety of
its collections.
These museums house objects from
material life together with [music]
another series of things that were
collected, sound recordings,
ethnographic documentation that shows us
forms of everyday life and their
development [music] since the arrival of
photography.
This building was designed in the 60s as
a museum of contemporary art.
Those were economic boom times for Spain
and the building which was planned and
constructed in those years was given the
best of everything as the magnitude and
the complexity of these technical
facilities show
like the system to keep the building at
specific levels of humidity and
temperature.
a system that was impressive for the
period.
[music]
Later, the anthropology museum, its
basements and stores filled up with a
strange universe, an unusual collection
of objects.
A kind of huge antique shop with wares
chosen at the time by expert eyes and
scrupously conserved since then.
These species are completely different,
able to teach us lessons about the
richness of diversity.
[music]
For a long time, the museum's cupboards
stored collections of clothing and
garments from very different social
levels, places, and periods. regional
costume, characteristic fabrics, crochet
work, lace, silk, linen, whose
restoration and conservation had to be
attended to by the creator.
Work with fabrics is always labor
intensive
and requires great attention. In the
fabric workshops, the curator had to
find an answer to all the problems and
needs such as finding the inks that are
closest to the color of the works on
which intervention is being carried out.
Washing which requires particular
attention to the fabric or the poor
stability of the fabric sinks.
or to the examination and correction
[music] of the damage that affects large
fabrics. For this last issue, the
curator has a large light table with a
grid structure which helps to [music]
line up the warp and weft of the
material correctly regardless of what
fibers that fabric is made of.
Fashions change and this fact concerns
[music] not only clothing but bodies
too.
Old clothing does not fit on modern
mannequins and so these must be [music]
rounded out a little before being used
in the workshop.
There is also much [music]
anthropological heritage made of
leather.
And this has a very important role in
the workshops.
Harnesses of [music] different kinds for
different purposes whose careful
examination and analysis provides new
data about their history.
Sometimes [music] this information
complements important aspects for
anthropological work.
The museum has another kind of piece
that is not normally found displayed in
a museum.
Objects that are much closer to us and
like farm harnesses, knives, or wooden
spoons, show the complexity [music] and
diversity of human objects.
It seems as if time has [music] acted on
these objects faster than it should
have,
or as if [music] it had done so on us.
In any case, the conservation of these
familiar utensils is no small problem.
Anthropology [music] museums are good
places to remember our childhood or even
better the childhoods of different
generations.
A collection of toys able to delight
young and old. Toys as innocent as the
children who used them. Toys from other
times when everything was different, but
those in which a new form of
entertainment was beginning to be seen.
one that was going to change the way of
seeing the world.
[music]
When cinematography appeared, it was
hardly anything other than a toy, a
fairground curiosity.
But the expressive imagination and
ambition of its pioneers soon set it on
the road to being a new art form based
on light and movement.
When sound was added to those first
trembling images, the new form of
expression became the most complete one
of all.
More than a century has passed since
then and cinema has produced hundreds of
thousands of works. The passage of time
on many of these has been merciless and
the world's film institutes like the
Spanish National Film Institute have an
ocean of cell on their hands whose
urgent conservation must be attended to.
This is no easy task because in cinema
work is not done on originals but on
copies. This is an art based on
reproduction and the material formally
used for the copies nitrates has a
dangerous tendency to combust. In fact,
they are true chemical bombs.
The criteria of cinematographic
restoration [music] are permanently
under debate. against the general
tendency of modern restoration which
rejects anything added. Some
cinematographic curators maintain that
cinema is a show and that interventions
should be imitative in order not to
distract from the film.
It is important to know as much as
possible about the work so as to know
how to undertake the task and this
requires [music] thorough systematic and
patient study beforehand like the work
of an alchemist. [music]
Sometimes [music] an old film can be
subject to study for more than 3 years
before a single still is taken.
It can be the case that there are
various versions which are quite unalike
for showing in [music] different
countries. It is common for years to
pass before all the materials can be
brought together. And finally, the work
of reconstruction from the original
negative can get underway.
In the sphere of cinematographic [music]
restoration, there are few who have
contributed as much as Spanish director
Juan Marin. With hundreds [music] of
kilometers of recorded film to his name,
he has spent many years attempting to
perfect and conserve the [music] art of
celoid at the Spanish National Film
Institute.
More than a restorer, Marine has always
been a keen researcher into new
mechanisms and processes for the
treatment of photographic material. an
innovative imagination able to insist
again and again on his ideas until they
are carried out.
[music]
Because when a reproduction of a film is
made, it should not be similar to the
original but the same, identical with
[music] no generation loss.
As well as its work restoring film, the
Spanish Film Institute has [music] the
responsibility of conserving
cinematographic collections that hold
more than 20,000 titles. This requires
an enormous effort from the point of
view [music] of storage and of
cataloging all the roles of film.
[music]
In principle, the film's materials have
meant the division of the entire
collection into two main groups.
While the modern material acetate does
not present any hazards, though it
requires specific conditions of
environmental stability [music] and
chemically neutral packaging, for the
old nitrate materials, it has been
necessary to create a specially designed
stack following strict safety
parameters.
This special stack has a number of
isolated cells, each one with its own
automatic alarm systems and shaft for
the removal of gases.
The cells are kept at a constant
temperature of 6° centigrade and a
relative humidity of 50%.
Furthermore, the film institute is in
charge of making copies on acetate of
the vast majority of these explosive
nitrate materials.
It's all
le.
In this way, it is possible to preserve
the great and not so important works of
art of our time for the knowledge and
enjoyment of future generations.
[music]
The creation and organization of an
important new museum is a unique
occasion for a global view of the many
things that the art curator must
consider.
The Tissen Bonisa Museum is one of the
great institutions of this kind, a
pioneer in its day. [music] Its
extraordinary collection includes works
from all periods and places of all
styles and all genre.
It is a result of many years of selected
acquisition in the international art
market.
[music]
Located on the Pio de Prado in Madrid
opposite the legendary museum of the
same name. It occupies the former Vieier
Mosa Palace built in the 18th century
and modified many times since then.
The Tissson Bonormisa Museum's air
conditioning is designed to hold the
temperature at between 20 and 23°
centigrade with a tolerance of more or
less a degree and a relative humidity of
around 55% with a tolerance of around
5%.
To install the tissa collection in
[music] the palace, it was necessary to
carry out detailed engineering and
architectural studies with the aim of
providing the old palace with the
infrastructure it would need to display
and [music] conserve the works with the
maximum guarantees of stability.
The difference between the concepts of
restoration [music] and conservation is
made clear here. Restoration is
necessary for objects whose material
existence is endangered due to the
action of external [music] agents over
time.
Conservation, on the other hand, focuses
on achieving [music] the best conditions
possible for the artwork in such a way
as the passage of time will never
endanger the piece's integrity.
Restoration means intervention, while
conservation can be understood as
constant [music] vigilance.
The Tissson Museum's collections, which
come from a modern private collection
created using strict criteria [music]
regarding the quality and material state
of the pieces, were already in good
condition before the museum was founded.
Therefore, the starting point was ideal
for attending to the [music]
conservation of the collection in a
uniform way.
The restoration department focuses on
the monitoring of the pieces and
preventative [music]
conservation. Bearing in mind the
factors that surround the work, this
involves detecting which of them might
cause damage in order to create barriers
and solve anomalies.
Due to the quality and variety of
[music] its collection, the museum
receives many requests for displaying
some of its pieces at large
international exhibitions of the most
varied kinds.
In these cases, the conditions demanded
by the center in terms of the transport
and security of its pieces are
necessarily very strict.
Special reinforced, [music] watertight,
and fireproof packaging is made for each
object, and the atmosphere within it is
the same as the one in which the work is
normally displayed.
[music] This packaging includes a number
of sensors that allow the conditions
inside to be known at all times, so that
a situation endangering the work will be
detected as soon as it [music] arises.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The same precautions are also extended
to certain pieces displayed in the
museum itself.
In this way, [music] all these marvels
of world art seem to have a safe future
for many, many years.
Each piece is a word in the neverending
dictionary of history and our commitment
[music] to these words is found rooted
within the human condition.
It is not a minor activity. It is the
[music] only path that we as a species
have been given to fight against the
unciring passage of time towards death
and forgetfulness.
>> [music]
[music]